# Leidy García Maza

# Chemist

Mail: ljohanagarcia@mail.uniatlantico.edu.co; Telephone: + 57 3043721093

As a young researcher I have developed different tasks in the area of Chemical Biology which has increased my technical and scientific abilities. Furthermore, through my academic training and results obtained during my research project I had the opportunity to participate in congresses both nationally and internationally. However, the most important thing has been to give back all the knowledge acquired to the community through projects with social impact.

# **Professional experience**

12/2021 - 12/2022 **Young researcher**, scholarships to strengthen CTel projects in health sciences with young talent and regional impact, El MINISTERIO y Fondo de Investigación en Salud (FIS).

#### Main task:

- Organic synthesis by conventional methods.
- Analysis and purification of compounds through chromatographic techniques (thin layer chromatography and column chromatography).
- Interpretation of IR, MS and NMR spectra.
- Planning and execution of bacterial growth inhibition tests and determination of virulence factors in ATCC and isolated bacterial pathogens as Pseudomonas aeruginosa and Escherichia coli.
- Writing scientific articles.
- Development of research projects with social impact.

02/2023 - present **Laboratory assistant**, Laboratorio de Investigación de Biología Molecular (LIBM), Universidad del Atlántico

#### Main task:

 Technical and scientific training for the student community belonging to the Faculty of Basic Sciences in the use of laboratory equipment and organic synthesis.

#### Education

• 2017 – 2023 **Chemist,** Bachelor's degree/ *Universidad del Atlántico*.

#### **Research Experience and Publications**

#### In Preparation

- **García M, L.J.**, Orosco F, D.F., Mendoza S, A.R., Rosales, W., Mendoza, E. & Meléndez G, C.M. (2023). A mild catalyzed imino Diels-Alder reaction. Synthesis of *N*-(2-(o-tolil)-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroquinoline-4-il)formamide derivatives as new regulatory agents of Quorum Sensing.
- Orosco F, D.F., García M, L.J. & Meléndez G, C.M. (2022). Resistencia a los antibióticos: estudio y prevención en áreas

priorizadas aledañas a la Universidad del Atlántico.

• **García M, L.J.**, Mendoza S, A.R., Hernández, M.A., <u>Vladimir V. Kouznetsov.</u>, Meléndez G, C.M. (2022). Review: Lamellarin D and pyrrolo[2,1-a]isoquinolines analogs as suitable models for developing anti-cancer agents.

## **Honors and Awards**

 Internship grant "Young Researcher", awarded by El MINISTERIO and Fondo de Investigación en Salud (FIS), under contract 519 of 2021 resulting from selective process 874 of 2020.

# **Additional languages**

English Read: C1 Speak: B2 Write: C1 Listen: B2

### **Presentations and Events**

Event: 35° Congresso Latino-Americano de Química e 61° Congresso Brasileiro de Química.

Type of event: International Congress

**Type of participation:** Poster

**Title:** A mild catalyzed Imino-Diels Alder reaction. Synthesis of N-(2-(o-tolyl)-1,2,3,4-tetrahydroquinoline-4-il)formamide

derivatives as antimicrobial agents.

Place: Rio de Janeiro, Brasil - Centro de Convenciones Windsor Florida, 14/11/2022 - 18/11/2022.

Event: Caribe Microbial Meeting 2022

Type of event: National Congress

Type of participation: Poster

Title: Efecto de una serie de derivados o-tolil(1,2,3,4-tetrahidroquinolin-4-il)formamida sobre el crecimiento bacteriano y

formación de Biofilm en Pseudomonas aeruginosa.

Place: Valledupar, Cesar - Universidad Popular del Cesar, 28/10/2022

Event: Il Congreso de Química del Caribe, Congreso Internacional

**Type of event:** *National Congress* **Type of participation:** *Assistant* 

Place: Barranquilla, Atlántico - Universidad del Atlántico, 27/02/2019 - 01/03/2019

# **Computational skills**

Excel: Advanced

**MATLAB:** Basic

#### **Further training**

08/2022 Bioinformatics Techniques for the Study of Proteins. Applications in Biomedical Research, Development and Diagnosis, Assistant. Fundación Global Disease Research Colombia. Duration: 40 hours.

#### References

• Carlos Mario Meléndez Gómez, Qco, PhD.

**Disciplines:** Biological chemistry. **Skills and expertise:** Researcher with experience in Organic Synthesis and Biomedical Chemistry. Specialist in strategies aimed at Diversity Organic Synthesis methodologies using cycloaddition reactions and tandem methods and biological analysis on the search for new anti-fungal, anti-parasitic and antimicrobial agents

Position: Professor (Associate).

Department: Programa de Química, Facultad de Ciencias Básicas - Universidad del Atlántico.

Location: Colombia.

carlosmelendez@mail.uniatlantico.edu.co

• Dency José Pacheco Lopéz, Qco, Dr. Sc.

**Disciplines:** Organic Chemistry. **Skills and expertise:** Organic Synthesis, Heterocyclic Compounds, Microwave Assisted Organic Synthesis.

Position: Professor (Associate).

Department: Programa de Química, Facultad de Ciencias Básicas - Universidad del Atlántico.

Location: Colombia.

dencypacheco@mail.uniatlantico.edu.co